<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 1999-2005 The Apache Software Foundation

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.2//EN" "http://apache.org/forrest/dtd/document-v12.dtd">
<document> 
  <header> 
    <title>Welcome to WSRP4J</title> 
  </header> 
  <body> 
    <section><title>Introduction</title>
      <p>
      Integration of content and application into portals has been a
      task requiring significant custom programming effort. Portal
      vendors or organizations running portals had to write special
      adapter portlets to allow portals to communicate with the
      different applications and content providers to accommodate a
      variety of interfaces and protocols. The <link
      href="ext:oasis-wsrp">OASIS Web Services for Remote Portlets
      (WSRP)</link> standard simplifies integration of remote
      applications/content into portals so that portal administrators
      can pick from a rich choice of services and integrate it in
      their portal without programming effort. As a result, WSRP
      becomes the means for content and application providers to
      provide their services to organizations running portals in a
      very easily consumable form.
      </p>

      <p>
      The Apache WSRP4J open source project was initiated by IBM to
      facilitate quick adoption of the WSRP standard by content and
      application providers and portal vendors. They can use WSRP4J as
      a platform for developing and hosting WSRP compliant web
      services. The OASIS WSRP standard will enable thousands of
      portals to aggregate content from tens of thousands of content
      and application providers offering hundreds of thousands of
      user-facing, pluggable web services for millions of end
      users/devices.
      </p>

      <p>
      We hope the WSRP4J project will kick start broad adoption of
      the WSRP standard and result in a large number of cool WSRP
      services running on free, open source Apache software.
      </p>

    </section>
    <note><strong>Disclaimer</strong>
      
      WSRP4J is an incubated subproject under the sponsorship of the
      Apache Software Foundation's (ASF) Web Services
      project. Incubation is required of all newly accepted projects
      until a further review indicates that the infrastructure,
      communications, and decision making process have stabilized in
      a manner consistent with other successful ASF projects. While
      incubation status is not necessarily a reflection of the
      completeness or stability of the code, it does indicate that
      the project has yet to be fully endorsed by the ASF.
      
   </note>
  </body>
</document>
